Aodong Li

SUMMARY

- Fifth-year Ph.D. candidate in Machine Learning at UC Irvine;
- Interested in solving machine learning problems from a probabilistic view, especially distribution shifts related topics;
- Experienced in anomaly detection, Bayesian time series, changepoint detection, continual learning, temporal word embeddings, deep reinforcement learning, and neural machine translation;
- Publication records in mainstream machine learning conferences NeurIPS/ICML;

Publications

<u>A. Li</u>, A. Sankararaman, B. Narayanaswamy, **ProHDT: Probabilistic Hash Embeddings for Dynamic and Temporal Tabular Data**, Under submission.

C. Fung, C. Qiu, <u>A. Li</u>, M. Rudolph, <u>Model Selection of Anomaly Detectors in the Absence of Labeled Validation Data</u>, Under submission.

<u>A. Li*</u>, C. Qiu*, M. Kloft, P. Smyth, S. Mandt, M. Rudolph. **Zero-Shot Anomaly Detection without Foundation Models**. NeurIPS, 2023.

<u>A. Li*</u>, C. Qiu*, P. Smyth, M. Kloft, S. Mandt, M. Rudolph. **Deep Anomaly Detection under Labeling Budget Constraints**. ICML 2023.

C. Qiu*, <u>A. Li*</u>, M. Kloft, M. Rudolph, S. Mandt. Latent Outlier Exposure for Anomaly Detection with Contaminated Data. ICML 2022.

<u>A. Li</u>, A. Boyd, P. Smyth, S. Mandt. **Detecting and Adapting to Irregular Distribution Shifts in Bayesian Online Learning**. NeurIPS 2021.

<u>A. Li</u>, R. Bamler, S. Mandt. Quantifying Gender Bias Over Time Using Dynamic Word Embeddings. SoCal Machine Learning Symposium 2020.

B. Foy, <u>A. Li</u>, J. McClung, R. Ranganath, J. Higgins. **Data-driven Physiologic Thresholds for Iron Deficiency Associated with Hematologic Decline**. American Journal of Hematology 2019.

<u>A. Li,</u> L. Sun, C. Li, Y. Wang, Y. Liu. **360-degree Video Streaming by Deep Reinforcement Learning**. Technical Report, November, 2018.

A. Li, S. Zhang, D. Wang. Enhanced Neural Machine Translation by Learning from Draft. APSIPA '17.

Work Experience

Amazon AWS AI Labs

Jun. - Sept. 2023

Applied Scientist Intern, work with Abishek Sankararaman, Murali Narayanaswamy

Research topic and deliverable: probabilistic models of dynamic and temporal tabular data; one paper submitted to AISTATS 2024.

- Propose probabilistic hash embedding (PHE) as a universal interface for data with dynamic dictionaries;
- Propose a temporal model that uses PHE for multi-task temporal tabular data;
- Derive a variational (Kalman filtering) inference algorithm for PHE and the temporal model:
- Our method provides Bayesian online learning capabilities on dynamic and temporal tabular data.

Bosch Center for Artificial Intelligence (BCAI)

Jun. 2022 - Sept. 2022

Machine Learning Research Intern, work with Maja Rudolph

Research topic and deliverable: deep active anomaly detection; one paper accepted at ICML 2023.

- Determine a set of conditions that generalize the anomaly score rankings from the queried to the unlabeled;
- Based on the conditions, we analyze querying strategies and propose k-means++-based diverse queries;
- Propose a novel semi-supervised anomaly detection loss that exploits both queried data and unlabeled data;
- Our proposed method significantly outperforms baselines on image, video, and tabular benchmarks.

Research topic: continuous-time latent switching dynamic models.

Qualcomm Technologies, Inc.

Jun. 2021 - Sept. 2021

Software Engineering Intern, work with Hilmi Enes Eğilmez

Work topic: neural video compression for autonomous driving.

- Apply state-of-the-art neural video compression to in-car fish-eye videos;
- Analyze the video noise patterns and develop a temporal denoising filter for better compression performance;
- The proposed method reaches the same performance as the best manually-designed video codec HEVC.

Research Experience

University of California, Irvine

Sept. 2019 - Present

Graduate Student Researcher, work with Stephan Mandt

Research topic and deliverable: online changepoint detection and adaptation; one NeurIPS 2021 paper.

- Consider online learning with distribution shifts that occur at an unknown rate and of unknown intensity.
- Derive a novel Bayesian online learning procedure to jointly infer and adapt to distribution shifts.
- Experiments on real-world data with concept shifts, image data with covariate shifts, and large-scale temporal texts show systematic improvements over baselines.

Research topic and deliverable: **deep anomaly detection**; one ICML 2022 paper; one ICML 2023 paper.

- Consider a new, practical problem setup when the training data contains unobserved anomalies;
- Propose a novel unsupervised anomaly detection algorithm inspired by outlier exposure.
- Experiments on three image datasets, 30 tabular data sets, and a video benchmark show consistent and significant improvements over the baselines.

Research topic and deliverable: quantifying gender bias in texts (NLP); one SoCal ML symposium 2020 paper.

- Quantify gender bias evolution through temporal word embeddings;
- Analyze three large temporal corpora (100M+ tokens) and automatically select the top gender-biased words;
- Find changes of gender bias align with historical events such as feminist movements.

CILVR Lab at New York University

Sept. 2018 - Jun. 2019

Graduate Student Researcher, work with Rajesh Ranganath

Research topic and delivery: Inference and machine learning for healthcare; one journal at American Journal of Hematology 2019.

- Consider the problem of estimating red blood cell's age distribution, which contributes the glycation in blood;
- Given very limited number of glucose measurements, infer the age distribution by deconvolving the glycation;
- Propose a data-driven method to re-define the iron-deficiency threshold for different gender groups.

New York University Video Lab

Jun. 2018 - Jun. 2019

Graduate Student Researcher, work with Yao Wang

Research topic and delivery: deep reinforcement learning on video streaming; one technical report.

- Apply advantage actor-critic algorithm (A2C) to manage the playback buffers in 3D VR video streaming;
- Incorporate the user vision information to improve the scheduler;
- Our system improves the video quality of a baseline system by 18%.

Center for Speech and Language Technologies at Tsinghua University May 2016 - June 2017 Research Intern, work with Dong Wang

Research topic and delivery: **neural machine translation (NLP)**; one APSIPA 2017 paper.

- Propose a two-stage drafting and refinement approach for neural machine translatioin;
- The proposed method improves the baseline by 0.9-2.5 BLEU score.

Compose Chapter 1 of the book Modern Machine Learning Techniques published by Tsinghua University Press.

EDUCATION

2017 - 2019 M.S. in Computer Science at New York University

2014 - 2017 M.Eng. in Electronic and Communication Engineering at BUPT

2010 - 2014 B.Eng. in Communication Engineering at **BUPT**

Miscellaneous

Teaching Assistants

Fall 2021, 2022 Deep Generative Models, UC Irvine

Fall 2019 Introduction to Machine Learning, UC Irvine

Spring 2019 Machine Learning, NYU

Fall 2018 Foundamental Algorithms, NYU

Honors

Fall 2019 Dean's Award, ICS@UC Irvine

Fall 2018 M.S. Thesis/Research Fellowship, CS@NYU

Academic Services

Reviewer for AISTATS 2021, ICML 2021-2023, NeurIPS 2021-2023, ICLR 2022-2023.

Skills

Python (PyTorch, TensorFlow, Numpy, Theano), IATEX, Bash, C/C++, JAVA, JavaScript, PHP, HTML, SQL.